Jérémy Ragusa

PhD in sedimentary geology and provenance analysis

3 rue Adrien Ligué Annemasse (France) ⑤ +33 6 21 84 53 34 ⋈ jeremy.ragusa@hotmail.fr শ jragusa.github.io

Professional Interests

Geologist with an expertise in the field of detrital sedimentology and regional geology (Prealps, Sub-alpine massifs). Very good knowledge in detrital rock analysis (composition, provenance, heavy minerals), statistics and programming language R. I'm autonomous and curious geologist with numerous computer skills (linux, inkscape, R) and knowledge sharing (wikipedia, openstreetmap, Chablais Geopark).

Professional Experiences

2018-2019 **Lecturer for Regional Geology (course and fieldtrip)**, *University of Geneva*, Switzerland.

2017 - present Scientific Advisor, Chablais Geopark, France.

EDUCATION

2015 - 2016 PostDoc, University of Geneva, Switzerland.

Writing papers. Preparing application for the Swiss National Science Foundation. Supervisor : Pascal Kindler.

2009 - 2015 **PhD Thesis in sedimentary geology**, *University of Geneva*, Switzerland.

Petrograpy, stratigraphy and provenance analysis of the Voirons Flysch (Gurnigel nappe) in the Chablais Prealps (France). Supervisor: Pascal Kindler.

2006 - 2009 Master Thesis in sedimentary geology, University of Geneva, Switzerland.

Study of heavy mineral population in the Voirons Flysch and the Samoëns Sandstones. Supervisor : Pascal Kindler.

2004 - 2005 **Master Thesis in paleoprimatology, paleontology and paleoenvironnements**, *University of Poitiers*, France.

Mineralogical study of the last pelitic sequence of Kollé 2 (Tchad): Paleoenvironmental implications

2001 - 2004 **Bachelor in geology**, *University of Dijon*, France.

PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

in review **Ragusa J, Kindler P**, Relation between grain size and modal composition in deep-sea gravity-flow deposits: diagenetic and provenance implications. Example from the Voirons Flysch (Gurnigel nappe, Chablais Prealps, France). Sedimentary Geology.

accepted **Ragusa J, Ospina-Ostios LM, Spezzaferri S, Kindler P**, Revision of the planktonic foraminiferal biostratigraphy of the Voirons Flysch (Chablais Prealps, Haute-Savoie, France). Swiss Journal of Geosciences.

2017 **Mulder T et al., 2017**, Carbonate slope morphology revealing a giant submarine canyon (Little Bahama Bank, Bahamas). Geology, 46:31–34, doi: 10.1130/G39527.1.

Ragusa J, Kindler P, Segvic B, Ospina-Ostios LM, 2017, *Provenance analysis of the Voirons Flysch (Gurnigel nappe, Haute-Savoie, France): Stratigraphic and paleogeographic implications. International Journal of Earth Sciences*, 106:2619–2651, doi: 10.1007/s00531-017-1474-9.

2013 **Ospina-Ostios LM, Ragusa J, Wernli R, Kindler P, 2013**, Planktonic foraminifera biostratigraphy as a tool in constraining the timing of flysch deposition: Gurnigel flysch, Voirons massif (Haute-Savoie, France). Sedimentology, 60:225–238, doi: 10.1111/sed.12013.

Unpublished Papers in Preparation

Ragusa J, Kindler P, Detrital evolution along the active margin of the Alpine Tethys using bulk-rock geochemistry. International Journal of Earth Sciences.

Ragusa J, Ospina-Ostios LM, Sartori M, Kindler P, Stratigraphic review of the Voirons Flysch (Voirons-Wägital complex, Haute-Savoie, France). Swiss Journal of Geosciences.

Professional Memberships

Swiss Geological Society.

Association des sédimentologues français.

AWARDS & GRANTS

2009 **Bourse Lombard**, *Master thesis Award (1000 CHF)*, Société de Physique et d'Histoire naturel de Genève.

Conference abstracts

2017 **Ragusa J, Kindler P (2017)**, Recognition of tectonic settings in collisional systems using bulkrock geochemistry: an example from the accretionary wedge of the Western Alps. Abstract for the 33rd International Meeting of Sedimentology, Toulouse.

Fabregas N, Mulder T, Hanquiez V, Gillet H, Ducassou E, Fauquembergue K, Principaud M, Conesa G, Conesa G, Le Goff J, Ragusa J, Bashah S, Bujan S, Reijmer JJG, Cavailhes T, Droxler A, Recouvreur A, Guiastrennec-Faugas L, Blank D, Seibert C (2017), Recognition of tectonic settings in collisional systems using bulk-rock geochemistry: an example from the accretionary wedge of the Western Alps. Abstract for the 33rd International Meeting of Sedimentology, Ttoulouse.

Pecouvreur A, Mulder T, Hanquiez V, Borgomano J, Reijmer JJG, Droxler A, Gillet H, Cavailhes T, Fabregas N, Guiastrennec-Faugas L, Fauquembergue K, Blank D, Bashah S, Bujan S, Seibert C, Ducassou E, Principaud M, Conesa G, Le Goff J, Ragusa J (2017), Large carbonate-fed deep-sea turbidite fan develloped at the mouth of a giant canyon along the Bahamian slope. Abstract for the 33rd International Meeting of Sedimentology, Toulouse.

Mulder T, Gillet H, Hanquiez V, Ducassou E, Fauquembergue K, Conesa G, Principaud M, Le Goff J, Ragusa J, Bujan S (2017), Carbonate slope morphology revealing bank-to-slope sediment transfer in Little Bahama Bank, Bahamas. Abstract for the European Geosciences Union (EGU) Meeting, Vienna.

2016 **Ragusa J, Kindler P (2016)**, Influence of grain-size and framework composition in deep-sea gravity-flow deposits. Example from the Voirons Flysch (Gurnigel Nappe, Chablais Prealps, France). Abstract for the 3rd Workshop of the Working Group of Sediment Generation (WGSG), Leuven.

Ragusa J, Kindler P (2016), Relation between grain-size and modal composition in deep-sea gravity-flow deposits. Example from the Voirons Flysch (Gurnigel nappe, Chablais Prealps, France). Abstract for the European Geosciences Union (EGU) Meeting, Vienna.

Ragusa J, Kindler P (2016), Relation between grain-size and modal composition in deep-sea gravity-flow deposits. Example from the Voirons Flysch (Gurnigel nappe, Chablais Prealps, France). Abstract for the SwissSed, Fribourg.

2015 **Ragusa J, Kindler P, (2015)**, Reconstructing the sediment provenance of the Voirons Flysch (Gurnigel Nappe, Haute-Savoie, France). Abstract for the 12th Alpine Workshop, Briançon.

Ospina-Ostios LM, Ragusa J (2015), The use biostratigraphic tools in dating the Voirons Flysch (Gurnigel Nappe, Haute-Savoie, France). Abstract for the 12th Alpine Workshop, Briançon.

- 2014 Ragusa J, Ospina-Ostios LM, Kindler P, (2014), Discovery of two major sediment sources for the Voirons Flysch (Gurnigel Nappe, Haute-Savoie, France). Abstract for the 19th International Sedimentology Congress (ISC), Geneva.
- 2013 **Ragusa J, Ospina-Ostios LM, Kindler P (2013)**, Provenance analysis of the Voirons Flysch (Gurnigel nappe, Haute-Savoie, France): highlighting two major sources. Abstract for the Swiss Geoscience Meeting (SGM), Lausanne.
 - Ragusa J, Ospina-Ostios LM, Kindler P (2013), Highlighting multiple sources for the Voirons Flysch (Gurnigel nappe, Chablais Prealps, Haute-Savoie, France) and stratigraphic implications. Abstract for the 1st School of Heavy Mineral Analysis, Milano.
- 2012 **Ragusa J, Ospina-Ostios LM, Kindler P (2012)**, Using Dickinson's method for a better understanding of the origin of the Voirons Flysch (Gurnigel nappe, Haute-Savoie, France). Abstract for the Swiss Geoscience Meeting (SGM), Berne.
- 2011 Ospina-Ostios LM, Ragusa J, Kindler P (2011), New sedimentological and biostratigraphic data from the Voirons Flysch (Voirons Massif, Gurnigel nappe, Haute-Savoie, France): Implications for Alpine geology. Abstract for the Swiss Geoscience Meeting (SGM), Bernouilli-Matter symposium, Zurich.
 - **Ragusa J, Ospina-Ostios LM, Kindler P (2011)**, Fault-controlled formation of a primary turbiditic channel within the Gurnigel Flysch in the Voirons Massif (Haute-Savoie, France) during the Late Eocene. Abstract for the Swiss Geoscience Meeting (SGM), Zurich.
- 2010 **Ospina-Ostios LM, Ragusa J, Kindler P (2010)**, New biostratigraphic data from the Voirons Sandstones (Voirons massif, Haute-Savoie, France): implications for the paleogeography for the Gurnigel nappe. Abstract for the Swiss Geoscience Meeting (SGM), Fribourg.
 - Ragusa J, Ospina-Ostios LM, Kindler P (2010), Preliminary results of the sedimentary petrography study of the Gurnigel flysch in the Voirons and Vouan massif. Abstract for the Swiss Geoscience Meeting, Fribourg.
- 2009 **Ospina-Ostios LM, Ragusa J, Kindler P (2009)**, New interpretation about turbidites in the Voirons Massif, Gurigel Nappe (Haute-Savoie, France). Abstract for the 27th International Association of Sedimentologists (IAS) Meeting, Alghero.

ORGANISATION

- 2014 Kindler P, Ragusa J, Slootman A. Pre-Meeting IAS-Student Field Trip: The Mt. Salève, 19th International Sedimentology Congress (ISC), Geneva.
- 2014 Kindler P. From passive margin to foreland basin: stratigraphy and sedimentology of the Bornes-Aravis massif (Haute-Savoie, France) from the Triassic to the Oligocene, 19th International Sedimentology Congress (ISC), Geneva.

SHORT COURSES

- 2014 4th Sedimentary Provenance Analysis, University of Göttigen, Germany.
- 2013 **1st School of Heavy Mineral Analysis**, University of Milano-Bicocca, Italy.

FIELD COURSES

- sep 2017 **Remnants of the ancient Tethys margins preserved in the Tasna, Platta, Err, Bernina and Ortler nappes in the Alps**, *Switzerland*, Swiss Geological Society, leader: Gianreto Manatschal (University of Strasbourg).
- dec 2016 **Carambar 2 (Deep-sea core drilling project)**, *Bahamas*, Ifremer, leader: Thierry Mulder (University of Bordeaux).
- sept 2015 **Workshop on Alpine Caronate Platforms**, *France*, Doctoral school of Western Switzerland (CUSO), leader: Pascal Kindler (University of Geneva).

- march 2013 Facies and structure of the Permian to Jurassic oceanic assemblage with a Panthalassic affinity of the Mino terrane, terrane central Japan, Japan, Doctoral school of Western Switzerland (CUSO), leader: Rossana Martini (University of Geneva).
- march 2012 Tectonics and sedimentation along an active plate boundary, New Zealand, Doctoral school of Western Switzerland (CUSO), leader: Guy Simpson (University of Geneva).
 - jan 2011 Modern and fossil carbonate environments, Bahamas, Doctoral school of Western Switzerland (CUSO), leader: Pascal Kindler (University of Geneva).

ANALYTICAL METHODS

Sedimentary petrography, sieving, staining feldspars, heavy mineral separation (SPT), counting.

Statistical analysis, cluster analysis, Principal component analysis, Pearson coefficient, Aitchison's log-ratio transformation.

SKILLS

Computer

OS Linux (Fedora), Windows Office LATEX, LibreOffice, MS Office Web HTML/CSS (basic), Git

Software R, Inkscape, QGIS (basic)

Languages

English good French native Russian basics

Interests

Leisures photo, hiking, running Contributor OpenStreetMap, Wikipedia